# Michael M Bowser

https://mbowser13.github.io

michael.m.bowser@gmail.com | 703.859.1135

I am a geospatial specialist from Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. I have been working with mapping technology since 2011, starting as a GIS technician preparing maps and providing data management and most recently working as a senior geospatial specialist developing open source web applications and add-ins with ArcObjects. I especially enjoy building applications with either C# or JavaScript and experimenting with new open source technology.

## **EXPERIENCE**

**Senior Geospatial Specialist -** Wetland Studies and Solutions, Inc. October 2013 – Present | Remote (Pittsburgh, PA)

- Worked as the GIS Lead and Geospatial Project Manager on multiple electric utility contracts
- Developed desktop applications and ESRI ArcGIS add-ins using C# and ArcObjects
- Used Leaflet, OpenLayers and GeoServer to create web mapping applications
- Introduced Python scripts and models to increase workflow efficiency for geospatial deliverables
- · Leveraged various analytical techniques to support existing projects and new business development
- Assisted staff with AutoCAD spatial data creation and spatial reference system conversions/scaling

**GIS Technician** – Gibson Thomas Engineering January 2013 - October 2013 | Latrobe, PA

- Constructed spatial databases for water and waste water utilities
- Prepared GIS mapping and developed data to support numerous sewer system models
- Worked with survey team to capture data for completing system maps

**GIS Technician** – The Carnegie Museum of Natural History May 2012 – May 2013 | Rector, PA

- Managed a research project to map tornado damage within the nature reserve
- Produced high quality trail maps for visitors, employees, and researchers of the property
- Created customized ArcGIS geodatabases for nature reserve research projects

**GIS Technician** – Institute for Mine Mapping, Archival Procedures and Safety September 2011 – January 2013 | Indiana, PA

- Analyzed and recorded geographic and attribute data from historical mining maps
- Preserved historical maps and documents through digital scanning or imaging
- Utilized historical map metadata to georeference map scans with ArcGIS
- Digitized underground mines and associated attribute data using ArcGIS Editor functionality

## **SKILLS**

ArcGIS Desktop (v10.x)

ArcGIS Server GeoServer

Leaflet

OpenLayers

ArcPad OGIS

ArcGIS Pro

Lidar

Spatial Databases

Cartography

C#.NET
Python
JavaScript
HTML
CSS

Microsoft Access

R

Visual Studio AutoCAD Open Source

# **EDUCATION**

Master of Geographic Information Systems – Penn State University

Major: Geographic Information Systems 2016 – 2018 (Expected)

**Bachelor of Arts** – Indiana University of Pennsylvania Major: Geography with GIS Option 2009 – 2013

# LINKS

GitHub: https://github.com/mbowser13

Personal Website: <a href="https://mbowser13.github.io/">https://mbowser13.github.io/</a>
LinkedIn: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/michaelbowser1/">https://www.linkedin.com/in/michaelbowser1/</a>

Company Website: http://www.wetlandstudies.com/

## **PUBLICATION**

Bowser, Michael M. *Black Birch Trail* [Map]. In: Gretchen N. Peterson. *GIS Cartography: A Guide to Effective Map Design*. Second Edition. Boca Raton, FL: CRC Press Taylor & Francis Group, 2015, p.276.